If we think about the aetiology of depressive disorders from a cognitive behavioral perspective,
Nếu ta nhìn nhận bệnh rối loạn trầm cảm từ khía cạnh nhận thức - hành vi,
the behavioral component suggests that depression is maintained by the lack of positive reinforcement
khía cạnh hành vi quan niệm trầm cảm được duy trì do thiếu sự động viên tích cực
that results from a person’s failure to engage in previously enjoyed activities.
nguyên nhân là do người bệnh không còn hứng thú với các hoạt động mình từng thích.
This in turn feeds into a sense of learned helplessness; a sense of utter powerlessness
Điều này lại tác động ngược lại tạo cảm giác bất lực hoàn toàn
in relation to the external environment.
trong việc tiếp xúc với môi trường bên ngoài.
Learned helplessness might be expressed in thoughts such as, “There is nothing I can
Cảm giác bất lực được thể hiện qua những suy nghĩ như"
do to make myself feel better.
"Mình không thể làm gì để khiến bản thân khá hơn cả.
I may as well just stop trying”.
Mình không nên cố gắng mà làm gì".
From the cognitive perspective, depression is very much about negative thoughts relating
Trên khía cạnh nhận thức, trầm cảm liên quan đến các suy nghĩ tiêu cực
to the self, the world and the future.
về bản thân, xã hội và tương lai.
People who are clinically depressed often, unsurprisingly, demonstrate what is referred
Những người thường xuyên chán nản hay có cách giải thích sự việc bi quan
to as a pessimistic explanatory style, where bad things are attributed to internal, stable
họ cho rằng việc không tốt là do các yếu tố nội tại, cố hữu gây ra,
and global factors; while positive things are attributed to external, random factors.
còn việc tốt cấu thành từ các yếu tố ngẫu nhiên bên ngoài.
For example, if I am clinically depressed and I happen to do very well on an exam, I
Ví dụ, nếu tôi bị trầm cảm và tôi lại tình cờ làm rất tốt một bài kiểm tra
might mentally explain this outcome to myself as: “I got a good result on that test because
trong thâm tâm tôi sẽ tự giải thích là: "Mình được điểm tốt là vì đề bài quá dễ"
the lecturer set a really easy exam”; not “I got a good result because I studied really
chứ không phải "Mình được điểm tốt vì mình
hard”.
đã học hành chăm chỉ".
On the other hand, if I do badly on the exam, I might say to myself &quot;I&#39;m dumb.
Ngược lại, nếu tôi không làm bài tốt, tôi sẽ tự nhận là mình ngu dốt,
I&#39;m worthless.
vô dụng.
I should have studied harder for that test.
Mình nên học hành chăm chỉ hơn.
I was totally underprepared.&quot;
Mình đã không chuẩn bị kĩ,
I&#39;m not saying to myself, &quot;That test was pretty hard.
Tôi sẽ không tự nhủ là: Bài kiểm tra này quá khó.
Everybody did badly on that test.&quot;
Mọi người đều làm bài tệ.